Catalog of the Literary Manuscripts in The Oscar Lion Collection of Walt Whitman, The New York Public Library
Published by The Walt Whitman Archive in collaboration with the University of Nebraska-Lincoln Libraries.
Literary Manuscripts in The Oscar Lion Collection of Walt Whitman
N/A
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892
poetry prose manuscripts
New York Public Library New York Public Library Humanities and Social Sciences Library Room 320 5th Avenue and 42nd Street New York, NY 10018-2788
This electronic catalog was created from catalogue records created by the New York Public Library, and obtained by The Walt Whitman Archive. The original papers and catalogue records are held in the Oscar Lion Collection of Walt Whitman at the New York Public Library.
Restrictions:
Access to the collection is restricted to qualified scholars and researchers through the Office of Special Collections, Room 316, Humanites and Social Sciences Library, New York Public Library. Requests for reproduction and/or permission to quote must be made in writing to the Curator and be accompanied by Estate permission.
Alternative Format:
Digital images of some items are available in the "Manuscripts" section of the Archive.
Scope and Content
In May, 1953, Mr. Oscar Lion presented to The New York Public Library a portion, and deposited there the remainder, of his remarkable collection of books, letters and manuscripts by or about Walt Whitman. Brought together during some thirty-five years of enthusiastic collecting, Mr. Lion's Whitmaniana totals over five hundred pieces, some of which are of great rarity and significance for the study of Whitman's life and writing. This catalog describes only those items deemed poetry and/or prose manuscripts.
Biographical Information
Subjects
Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892; Whitman, Walt, 1819-1892--Manuscripts; Poets, American--19th century
Item List
- Night of south winds | The crowds naked in the bath, about 1855; nyp.00078; xxx.00048; poetry handwritten 1 leaf approximately 19.5 x 19 cm.
  A manuscript that includes language that appeared in the first poem of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass, in what later became section 21 of Song of Myself. On the verso are lines that eventually found their way into section 31 of the same poem. The manuscript was bound by the collector.
- vain the mastodon, about 1855; nyp.00079; xxx.00048; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten 18.5 by 19.7 cm. (irregular)
  The recto contains draft lines for the first poem of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass, eventually titled Song of Myself. These lines are from sections 31 and 32, as numbered in the 1891-92 edition. On the verso are two prose notes, the first about the frequent meanness of men of high social standing and the second about the wisdom of keeping "clean inside and out." The leaf was formerly cut between the verso-side notes, probably by Whitman, and has been rejoined.
- Leaves of Grass. Brooklyn, New York, 1855., nyp.00522; xxx.00001; poetry 4 p. 1., xii, (1) 14-95 p. front. (port.) 30 cm.
  Whitman's own copy, with handwritten notes and the original pink paper covers, of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. Into this copy, Whitman has tipped 8 booklets of manuscripts, 52 leaves in all, as well as typed copies of six of the booklets. The cover contains a handwritten note by Horace L. Traubel about the finding of this copy. With holograph letter of Anne Montgomerie Traubel to Oscar Lion, dated May 12, 1928, describing the finding of this copy after Whitman's death.
- Notes Passage to India, 1870-1871; nyp.00080; xxx.00496; poetry 23 leaves, numbered 1-21, with pages designated "5 1/2" and "5 3/4." handwritten print 25.2 by 20 to 31.2 by 20.5 cm.
  Revised draft of the poem Passage to India, first published in a small volume of the same name in 1871. It was later included as a supplement to the second issue of the 1871 edition of Leaves of Grass. At some point before March 15, 1870, Whitman had an early draft of the poem set in print by Andrew and Thomas Rome (the printers of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass). Whitman then used the printed pages to make edits and corrections, which he subsequently sent to publisher J.S. Redfield, who ultimately printed the finished book. Since this particular draft contains portions of the printed poem pasted onto the manuscript pages, it most likely dates from after March 1870. At the repository, the draft is accompanied by a typewritten memorandum by Emory Holloway, as well as typewritten letters from Amy Lowell and Clifton Joseph Furness to Oscar Lion; images of these items are not available.
- Old Age Echoes, 1889-1891; nyp.00081; xxx.00397; poetry 1 leaf handwritten 20.1 by 19.5 cm
  Lightly revised draft of a poem titled Sounds of the winter too. Under the title Sounds of the Winter, the poem was one of four belonging to the Old Age Echoes cluster, first published in Lippincott's Magazine 47 ( March 1891 ) and then reprinted in Good-bye My Fancy ( 1891 ). The writing on the verso (not in Whitman's hand) makes reference to Good-Bye My Fancy and to Sounds of Winter, as well as to a Putnam 1902 Edition. There is also a postmark dated 18 October 1889.
- The Biography, about 1867; nyp.00082; xxx.00032; poetry 1 leaf handwritten 18 by 11 cm
  Heavily revised draft of the poem When I Read the Book that extends onto the verso. The poem was first published in the 1867 edition of Leaves of Grass before being revised for inclusion in the Inscriptions cluster of the 1871 edition. This draft seems to correspond more closely to the earlier version of the poem, although it contains several lines that do not appear in either version.
- Have I no word for thee | To the Year 1889, about 1889; nyp.00083; xxx.00389; poetry 1 leaf handwritten 12.5 by 19.5 cm
  About seven lines, with revisions, toward the poem To the Year 1889. The writing on the verso (not in Whitman's hand) makes reference to the title of this poem, as well as to Good-Bye My Fancy and a "Putnam 1902 Edition." To the Year 1889 was first published on January 5, 1889, in the Critic. The poem was retitled To the Pending Year for its inclusion in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 )
- The Blue Book, about 1860; nyp.00015; xxx.00001; poetry 243 leaves handwritten
  Of nearly as much significance as Whitman's copy of the 1855 Leaves is his copy of the Boston, 1860-61 edition, the famous Blue Book. It is this volume, in blue paper wrappers, that was discovered in Whitman's desk by Secretary of the Interior James Harlan, leading to Whitman's dismissal from the Department on June 30, 1865. Documenting this event in Whitman's life in Washington, the Lion Collection also includes a group of seven letters and documents relating to his work in the Departments of the Interior and Justice. Among these are Secretary Harlan's letter of dismissal, and a memorandum in Whitman's hand recording a conversation with W. T. Otto of the Department of the Interior about the finding of the Blue Book in Whitman's desk; images of these items are unavailable.
  The book itself is heavily corrected and revised throughout in Whitman's hand, in preparation for later editions, though in fact Whitman never implemented many of the changes he contemplated. The Blue Book is another remarkable example of his lifelong habit of editing and rewriting his poems. The flyleaf is inscribed: "Property of Horace L. Traubel / Received from Walt Whitman May 23d 1890 —W. saying: 'You fellows value these curios more than I do. This will help you to see how the book grew, if that is anything. But I guess you would know how it grew if you never possessed the book. The book is a milepost... This gives a glimpse into the work shop.. .'"
- [The Epos of a Life], 1865–1871; nyp.00521; xxx.00353; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A cancelled poetry manuscript that is related to Inscription, the prefatory poem of the 1867 edition of Leaves of Grass, which was later revised as Small the Theme of My Chant. Other manuscripts held at Dartmouth and the Library of Congress (Charles E. Feinberg) open with the same revised line, though the published poem does not. An image of the verso is unavailable.
- Passage to India, 1869–1871; nyp.00077; xxx.00496; poetry 13 leaves handwritten
  Notes and drafted lines for the poem Passage to India, first published in a small volume of the same name in 1871. It was later included as a supplement to the second issue of the 1871 edition of Leaves of Grass. The first page features the watermark of "Platner & Porter, Congress" in the upper right-hand corner.
- [Love is the cause of causes], 1854; nyp.00129; xxx.00845; prose poetry 12 leaves handwritten
  Two cancelled drafts of a poem that was unpublished during Whitman's lifetime. It was published posthumously as [Love is the cause of causes] in the "Uncollected Poems" section of Leaves of Grass: Comprehensive Reader's Edition, edited by Harold W. Blodgett and Sculley Bradley ( 1965 ). These manuscripts are part of a larger notebook, in which Whitman recorded a series of prose notes. The poetry drafts are surfaces 9 and 12. Edward Grier dates the notebook to 1854, citing the reference to the wreck of the San Francisco and the opening of "a marble church" in New York City (on the notebook's first page), which Emory Holloway identifies as the Marble Collegiate Church, both of which occurred in 1854 (see Grier, Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts [New York: New York University Press, 1984] 1:128).
- [May 17 '81—Glendale], 1881; nyp.00527; xxx.00816; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  Prose notes, dated May 17, 1881, that may have contributed to Cedar-Apples, first published in Specimen Days & Collect ( 1882-83 ).
- [writing letters, by the bed-side], 1863–1864; nyp.00253; xxx.00846; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A partial draft of Our Wounded and Sick Soldiers—Visits Among Army Hospitals, At Washington, on the Field, and here in New-York, first published in the New York Times, 11 December 1864. Though parts of Our Wounded and Sick Soldiers were partially reprinted in the New York Weekly Graphic ( 1874 ), Memoranda During the War ( 1876 ), and Specimen Days ( 1882 ), the portion which appears in this draft was not reprinted until after Whitman's death in The Wound Dresser ( 1898 ). An image of the verso is unavailable.
- [will you have the walls], 1850–1855; nyp.00085; xxx.00848; poetry prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A series of poetic lines with no known relationship to Whitman's published writings. On the verso of this manuscript are cancelled prose notes that also bear no known connection to Whitman's published works.
- One good of knowing One good of knowing the great politics of nature, about 1860; nyp.00124; xxx.00152; poetry prose handwritten 1 leaf
  A prose note on "the great politics of nature" that Whitman reworked and used in the poem To a President, first published in Leaves of Grass ( 1860–1861 ), and reprinted in subsequent editions of Leaves.
- I admire a beautiful woman just as much directly, 1845–1892; nyp.00125; xxx.00667; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  About three lines of poetry, with revisions, of unknown relation to Whitman's published work. On the verso is a prose fragment addressing the question of how to establish and raise the "character of cities," also of unknown relation to Whitman's published work.
- All moves unwittingly or halts, about 1856; nyp.00126; xxx.01004; prose handwritten 1 leaf
  Heavily revised prose notes that constitute a partial draft of the Letter to Ralph Waldo Emerson, which Whitman published in the "Leaves-Droppings" section of the 1856 edition of Leaves of Grass.
- Inscription To the Reader at the entrance of Leaves of Grass, 1860–1867; nyp.00520; xxx.00024; xxx.00309; xxx.00353; poetry 6 leaves handwritten
  One of a series of draft introductions Whitman prepared for Leaves of Grass, but which were never printed during his lifetime. This particular introduction, composed entirely in verse, was reworked and revised multiple times. Though Inscription To the Reader at the entrance of Leaves of Grass did not appear in print as a distinct and cohesive piece until collected by Clifton Joseph Furness in Walt Whitman's Workshop ( 1928 ), portions of this draft were distilled into One's-self I Sing, first published as Inscription in the 1867 edition of Leaves of Grass. Whitman revised this poem before including it as One's-self I Sing in 1871, dropping some of the lines only to reintroduce them in Sands at Seventy ( 1888 ), under the title Small the Theme of My Chant. Both One's-self I Sing and Small the Theme of My Chant appeared in the 1891-92 edition of Leaves of Grass. Lines from this manuscript were also revised and used in the poem So Long!, which first appeared in the 1860-61 edition of Leaves of Grass. The verso of the last leaf is blank and an image is unavailable.
- Inscription at the entrance of Leaves of Grass, 1860–1867; nyp.00517; xxx.00024; xxx.00353; poetry 3 leaves handwritten
  One of a series of draft introductions Whitman prepared for Leaves of Grass, but which were never printed during Whitman's lifetime. This particular introduction, composed entirely in verse, was reworked and revised multiple times. Though Inscription at the entrance of Leaves of Grass did not appear in print as a distinct and cohesive piece until collected by Clifton Joseph Furness in Walt Whitman's Workshop ( 1928 ), portions of this draft were distilled into One's-self I Sing, first published as Inscription in the 1867 edition of Leaves of Grass. Whitman revised this poem before including it as One's-self I Sing in 1871, dropping some of the lines only to reintroduce them in Sands at Seventy ( 1888 ), under the title Small the Theme of My Chant. Both One's-self I Sing and Small the Theme of My Chant appeared in the 1892 edition of Leaves of Grass. Images of the versos are unavailable.
- To the Reader at the Entrance of Leaves of Grass, 1860–1867; nyp.00515; xxx.00024; xxx.00309; xxx.00353; poetry 4 leaves handwritten printed
  One of a series of draft introductions Whitman prepared for Leaves of Grass, but which were never printed during Whitman's lifetime. This particular introduction, composed entirely in verse, was reworked and revised multiple times. Though To the Reader at the Entrance of Leaves of Grass did not appear in print as a distinct and cohesive piece until collected by Clifton Joseph Furness in Walt Whitman's Workshop ( 1928 ), portions of this draft were distilled into One's-self I Sing, first published as Inscription in the 1867 edition of Leaves of Grass. Whitman revised this poem before including it as One's-self I Sing in 1871, dropping some of the lines only to reintroduce them in Sands at Seventy ( 1888 ), under the title Small the Theme of My Chant. Both One's-self I Sing and Small the Theme of My Chant appeared in the 1892 edition of Leaves of Grass. Lines from this manuscript were also revised and used in the poem, So Long!, which first appeared in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass.
- [The best of the two Introductions], 1860–1865; nyp.00514; xxx.00524; prose 8 leaves handwritten
  One of a series of draft introductions Whitman prepared for Leaves of Grass, but which were never printed during Whitman's lifetime. Though this introduction was not printed as a complete and distinct piece until collected by Clifton Joseph Furness in Walt Whitman's Workshop ( 1928 ), portions of this draft were used in Democratic Vistas ( 1871 ). An image of the verso of the final leaf is unavailable.
- [Dec 23, 1864 good—& must be used], 1860–1864; nyp.00513; xxx.00524; prose 8 leaves handwritten
  One of a series of draft introductions Whitman prepared for Leaves of Grass, but which were never printed during Whitman's lifetime. Though this introduction was not printed as a complete and distinct piece until collected by Clifton Joseph Furness in Walt Whitman's Workshop ( 1928 ), portions of this draft were used in Democratic Vistas ( 1871 ).
- [Thuswise it comes], 1860–1867; nyp.00516; xxx.00022; poetry 3 leaves handwritten
  One of a series of draft introductions Whitman prepared for Leaves of Grass, but which were never printed during Whitman's lifetime. This particular introduction, composed entirely in verse, is most closely related to Inscriptions, which first appeared in the 1867 edition of Leaves of Grass. However, no lines from this manuscript can be directly linked to any part of Inscriptions. No other relationship to Whitman's published work is known.
- Loveblows Loveblows Loveblossoms, 1850–1855; nyp.00122; xxx.00673; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A list of words starting with "Love-" (e.g. "Loveroot"), many of them plant metaphors that could be read as referring to parts of the body, in particular to the genitals. The words are likely connected to line 14 of the 1855 version of the poem that would eventually be titled Song of Myself.
- The whip sting ray The whip sting ray, about 1856; nyp.00094; xxx.00268; poetry prose handwritten 1 leaf
  A manuscript fragment discussing the dangers of the "whip sting ray"—much "dreaded by fishermen" in the New York area. These prose notes bear no known relationship to Whitman's published works. However, at the top of the manuscript are cancelled lines which read: "and winrows are the green backed spotted mossbonkers... the fishermen stand in negligent ease, poised on their strong limbs—." Whitman used these cancelled lines, in slightly revised form, in the poem that would eventually be known as A Paumanok Picture. First published as part of Poem of Salutation in Leaves of Grass ( 1856 ), then as part of Salut au Monde in the 1860–1861, 1867, and 1871–1872 editions of Leaves; these lines were later extracted and published as a separate poem, A Paumanok Picture, in Leaves of Grass ( 1881–82 and 1891–92 ). An image of the verso is unavailable.
- Have you known that Have you known that your limbs must not dangle, 1850-1860; nyp.00095; xxx.00665; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  This scrap may have been part of a larger leaf, which began with the line "Who wills with his own brain" (see Oscar Lovell Triggs' The Complete Writings of Walt Whitman [New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1902] 3:269). The connection of the lines on this scrap to any of Whitman's published work is uncertain. An image of the verso is unavailable.
- I heat the hot cores I heat the hot cores within, 1850-1860; nyp.00088; xxx.00668; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Two lines of poetry, with some revisions, that make reference to the core of the Earth and to the sun. The connection between these lines and Whitman's published work is unknown. An image of the verso is unavailable.
- I shall venerate hours and days I shall venerate hours and days, 1850-1860; nyp.00089; xxx.00682; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  About four lines of poetry, one of which contains the colloquial word "limpsey" (weak), of which Whitman was fond. The three lines on the verso bear some resemblance in theme to the fifth poem in Chants Democratic, a cluster of poems first published in the 1860-61 edition of Leaves of Grass.
- First, to me First, to me, come the People, about 1890; nyp.00091; xxx.00560; prose 1 leaf handwritten
  A prose fragment that Whitman used in the essay, American National Literature, first published in the North American Review in March 1891, under the title Have We a National Literature? The essay was reprinted in Good-Bye My Fancy ( 1891 ) before finally being collected in Complete Prose Works ( 1892 ).
- [sea—cabbage] sea-cabbage, 1855—1860; nyp.00093; xxx.00243; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A list of words and notes, mostly related to the sea. The last line of this manuscript is similar to a line Whitman used in Miracles. Compare the draft line, "sound of walking barefoot ankle deep in the edge of the water," with the published line, "or wade with naked feet along the beach, just in the edge of the water." Miracles first appeared in the 1856 edition of Leaves of Grass under the title, Poem of Perfect Miracles.
- Lo, space, eternal, nyp.00098; xxx.00672; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Three lines of poetry, with revisions. No connection to Whitman's published poetry is known.
- [born at all is equally wonderful] born at all is equally wonderful, before 1855; nyp.00100; xxx.00250; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A poetic fragment which was used slightly revised in Who Learns My Lesson Complete?, a poem that first appeared as part of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. Revised versions of this poem appeared throughout the editions of Leaves of Grass, the final title first appearing in 1871–1872. On the verso of this manuscript is a list of words, whose relationship to Whitman's published work is unclear.
- Points in Proem Points in Proem, nyp.00121; xxx.00677; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Notes on some material to incorporate into the "Proem" Whitman drafted in another manuscript.
- Proem Proem, nyp.00118; xxx.00678; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  Draft of a line justifying the poet's inclusion of "amativeness" as a topic in his poems. The title "Proem" suggests that this may be the draft of a passage for a prefatory poem.
- Enter into the thoughts Enter into the thoughts of the different theological faiths, before 1855; nyp.00112; xxx.00048; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A manuscript containing lines about "enter[ing] into the thoughts of the different theological faiths." Edward Grier credits R. M. Bucke with pointing out the similarity of the text with a portion of Song of Myself (specifically, the portion that would become section 43 in the Deathbed edition). Once part of a larger scrap that began with "For example, whisper." Edward F. Grier credits R. M. Bucke with pointing out the "similarity of the text to Song of Myself (1855), sec. 43, ll. 1096-1110. The date is undoubtedly before 1855."
- [I can tell of the long besieged city] I can tell of the long besieged city, 1845–1855; nyp.00511; xxx.00048; prose poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A scrap of paper with poetic lines that were used in revised form in the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. The lines contained in this manuscript were eventually used in the poem ultimately titled Song of Myself. On the verso of this scrap is a prose fragment with no known connection to Whitman's published work.
- Reflections, nyp.00119; xxx.00679; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A heavily revised draft of about five lines, with the suggested titles of "Reflections" and "Shadows."
- Poem, nyp.00120; xxx.00675; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A newspaper clipping pasted onto a piece of paper, with Whitman's handwritten notes in the margins. The title "Poem" and the first note indicate that he is deriving an idea for a new poem from the newspaper excerpt, which deals with the "ennobling" effect of struggles and hardships one may face in life.
- A remembrance (A remembrance), nyp.00117; xxx.00681; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A heavily revised line toward what seems to have been intended as a poem titled "A remembrance," honoring the air we breathe and also "a breed of full-sized young men and women."
- A string of Poems A string of Poems, before 1859; nyp.00115; xxx.00683; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  This scrap reads, in its entirety, "A string of Poems (short, etc.), embodying the amative love of woman—the same as Live Oak Leaves do the passion of friendship for man." Since, as Fredson Bowers points out in his introduction to Whitman's Manuscripts: "Leaves of Grass" (1860): A Parallel Text (lxxiii-lxxiv), Whitman dropped the title "Live Oak Leaves" in late spring, 1859, and adopted calamus as his symbol of manly love, the date must be earlier.
- Appendage Appendage, 1850–1870; nyp.00111; xxx.00001; poetry 1 leaf handwritten
  A list of trial titles, probably for annexes or supplements to Leaves of Grass.
- Like Earth O River Sailing Down the Mississippi, nyp.00106; xxx.00671; xxx.00522; poetry 1 leaf handwritten